<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>KYLE WALKER DATA</title>
    <link>/tags/arcgis/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on KYLE WALKER DATA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>kwalkerdata@gmail.com (Kyle Walker)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>kwalkerdata@gmail.com (Kyle Walker)</webMaster>
    <copyright>(c) 2017 Kyle Walker</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/arcgis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to use the Rodeo IDE with ArcGIS Pro</title>
      <link>/2017/02/rodeo-arcpro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 04:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>kwalkerdata@gmail.com (Kyle Walker)</author>
      <guid>/2017/02/rodeo-arcpro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had a need to automate some GIS operations using &lt;a href=&#34;https://pro.arcgis.com/en/pro-app/&#34;&gt;ArcGIS Pro&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pro.arcgis.com/en/pro-app/arcpy/get-started/what-is-arcpy-.htm&#34;&gt;ArcPy Python site package&lt;/a&gt;. As of version 1.3, ArcGIS Pro ships with Anaconda as its Python installation, which makes it easier to work with ArcGIS as part of a broader data science workflow. I wanted to do my work in my Python IDE of choice, &lt;a href=&#34;http://rodeo.yhat.com/&#34;&gt;Yhat’s Rodeo&lt;/a&gt;; however, this didn’t work out of the box. I’m sharing the process I used to connect Rodeo to ArcGIS Pro’s Anaconda Python 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For IDEs to access ArcGIS Pro licensing regardless of whether or not you have an internet connection, you’ll need to enable offline access. Click the &lt;strong&gt;Projects&lt;/strong&gt; tab in ArcGIS Pro, then choose the &lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt; option; scroll down and check the appropriate box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://walkerke.github.io/img/blog/arcpro1.PNG&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, click the &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; option from the menu on the left. From here, search for the &lt;strong&gt;jupyter&lt;/strong&gt; package and install it, which should install Jupyter and its associated libraries. This step is necessary to get Rodeo to work with ArcGIS Pro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://walkerke.github.io/img/blog/arcpro2.PNG&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, launch your Rodeo application, and click &lt;strong&gt;Rodeo &amp;gt; Preferences&lt;/strong&gt; to switch its &lt;a href=&#34;http://rodeo.yhat.com/docs/#using-conda-environments&#34;&gt;conda environment&lt;/a&gt;. Click the &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; tab, and change your Python Command by navigating to the Python executable associated with the &lt;strong&gt;arcgispro-py3&lt;/strong&gt; conda environment; you can find it where ArcGIS Pro is installed on your machine in &lt;code&gt;ArcGIS\Pro\bin\Python\envs\arcgispro-py3\&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://walkerke.github.io/img/blog/arcpro3.PNG&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click OK, import &lt;strong&gt;arcpy&lt;/strong&gt;, and write scripts to automate ArcGIS as usual!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://walkerke.github.io/img/blog/arcpro4.PNG&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD






/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>